Here we are for the day.
오늘의 목적지예요
2.1 notebook.
2번요 공책 한 권요
And don't let it be said that I don't ever do anything for you.
내가 당신을 위해 아무것도 안 한다고 하지 말아요
As you will see, I have gone out on a limb with this one for your pleasure.
보시면 알겠지만, 당신의 즐거움을 위해 위험을 감수했어요
Uh, so, uh, again, we are just going to be visualizing our data store for a moment now.
다시 말씀드리지만 잠시 데이터 저장소를 시각화해 볼게요
Um, and to do that, we do some imports.
그러기 위해서는 수입을 해야 해요
And there is then a cell here where we select the maximum number of data points that we want to show
그리고 셀이 있는데요 벡터의 시각화에서 보여주고자 하는 데이터 포인트의
in a visualization of our vectors.
최대 개수를 선택하는 곳이죠
And my recommendation is that you stick with 10,000 which is a safe number.
저는 10,000개를 추천합니다 그게 안전한 숫자죠
You get a nice image and your machine will not be ground to a halt.
이미지도 좋고 기계도 멈추지 않을 거예요. Get it.
But that would be no fun for you.
하지만 그건 재미없잖아요
And I wanted to show you what it looks like if you get all 400,000 data points to show, but it's precarious
400,000개의 데이터 포인트를 모두 모으면 어떻게 되는지 보여드리고 싶었는데 불안정하고 제 기계가
and it puts my machine in a very unsafe position that it might crash at any moment.
위험한 상황에 처하게 돼요 언제라도 충돌할 수 있죠 Get up
And indeed, in preparing for this, I have had my machine crash a couple of times and had to even start
이걸 준비하면서 제 기계가 몇 번 고장 났는데 이 주피터 노트북으로 다시
again with this Jupyter notebook, so I do not recommend you do this unless you have a very powerful
시작해야 했어요 그러니 아주 강력한 기계가 아닌 이상 이걸 하지 마세요
Um, so, uh, in the code, we, we, uh, we connect to the vector database.
코드 안에서 우리는 벡터 데이터베이스에 연결돼요
We have some code which is essentially a duplicate of what we already did in the rag week.
코드가 있어요 래그 주간에서 이미 한 걸 복사한 거죠
Uh, when we, um, got some did some pre work to collect from the vector data, store the objects themselves,
벡터 데이터 수집을 위한 사전 작업을 할 때 개체 자체와 문서 메타데이터의
the documents, their categories that are in the metadata, and then color pick out the right color
카테고리를 저장하고 적절한 색깔을 골라 여러 점을 식별할
that would be able to allow us to identify the different points.
수 있게 했죠
And remember when I show you this, the thing that's super important to keep in mind is that the vectorization
이걸 보여드릴 때 기억하셔야 할 아주 중요한 건 벡터화 프로세스, 각각의 문서에
process, the process of deciding what vector to use for each of the documents, was based purely on
대해 어떤 벡터를 사용할지를 결정하는 프로세스는 순전히 문서 그 자체의 설명에
the description of the documents themselves.
근거했다는 거죠
It was only based on the language in in each product description that we pulled all 400,000 product
각 제품 설명의 언어를 바탕으로 400,000개의 제품을 전부 추출했어요
The fact that we happen to know which which ones are appliances, which ones are automotive, which
어떤 게 전자 기기인지 자동차에 달린 건지 어떤 게 전자 기기인지
ones are electronics.
알 수 있죠
The model is not told that the model that builds the vector is just given the text.
모델은 벡터를 구축하는 모델이 텍스트를 받는다는 걸 몰라요
So it's helpful to then color it in so we can see.
그래서 볼 수 있게 색칠하는 게 도움이 되죠
All right.
좋아요
This is the landscape of all of the vectors.
이게 모든 벡터의 풍경이에요
Are there trends.
유행이 있나요?
Can we see that the model was able, just through the language, to separate out some of the different
모델이 언어를 통해서 거기 있는 다른 종류의 것들을 분리할
kinds of thing that's there?
수 있었나요?
But this this kind of thing, this category was not part of the text that it vectorized.
하지만 이런 종류의 카테고리는 벡터화 된 텍스트의 일부가 아니에요
Okay.
네
So anyway, with that, uh, this is now doing the t-SNE, uh, dimension reduction process, and this
어쨌든 이제 t-SNE 즉, 치수 감소 과정을 거치고 있어요 제 기계에
took about an hour to run on my machine.
한 시간 정도 걸렸죠
Uh, for the 400,000 it would take, it should be five minutes or something for 10,000.
400,000시간이면 5분 정도 걸릴 거예요 10,000시간요
Uh, and then we can create a scatter plot, much as we did before.
그럼 전처럼 분산도를 만들 수 있어요
Uh, and then we can plot this scatter plot.
그러면 분산도를 그릴 수 있어요
And now I will show you what it looks like.
이제 어떻게 생겼는지 보여드릴게요
And it's super slow to to do this on my machine.
제 컴퓨터로 하는 건 정말 느려요
But this rather beautiful thing here is the result of looking at all of the vectors.
여기 이 아름다운 것은 모든 벡터를 관찰한 결과예요
Uh, let me try and and and shrink this a little bit.
비트를 좀 줄여 볼게요
The machine is running very slowly.
기계가 아주 느리게 돌아가요
Uh, but you get a sense of the vector space from all 400,000 vectors.
400,000마리의 벡터를 통해 벡터 공간을 느낄 수 있어요. Get it.
Here we go.
시작할게요
It's just coming into view now.
이제 보이네요
And the important thing to see is that.
중요한 건 이거예요
Yes, indeed.
네, 맞아요
Uh, there it goes.
저기 가네요
Agonizingly slow.
고통스러울 정도로 느려요
Yes, indeed.
네, 맞아요
Different products have ended up most of the time in different territories, in vector space, with
다른 제품들은 대부분 다른 지역에서 벡터 공간에 놓이게 됩니다
some clusters that appear to be, uh, near each other.
서로 가까운 클러스터들에서요
And when you have a smaller number in here, you can go in and investigate the different ones and satisfy
더 적은 수의 가전제품이 있다면 다른 것들을 살펴보고
yourself that the reason that they are potentially in another territory is because they are perhaps
스스로 만족할 수 있습니다. 잠재적으로 다른 영역에 있는 이유는 가전제품과
products that straddle both being appliances and electronics or something like that.
전자 제품과 양쪽에 걸쳐 있기 때문일 수도 있어요.
So this is really just for for an opportunity to look at the data and investigate it and understand
데이터를 보고 조사하고 이해할 기회를 위한 거예요 문서와 관련된 벡터를
it and just give a little bit more intuition about what does it mean to create vectors associated with
생성하고 저장하는 것이 어떤 의미인지 직관적인 것을 좀 더
documents, um, and to, to store them.
보여주기 위해서요
Uh, and so it gives you that hands on tangible sense.
그래서 눈에 보이는 감각을 손으로 만질 수 있어요
And I hope that you enjoy this image, and I hope it was worth almost breaking my box.
즐겁게 감상하시길 바라요 제 상자를 부술 뻔했는데도 가치가 있었길 바라요
And hopefully you're doing it with a smaller number.
더 적은 숫자로도 가능하길 바라요
And I will see you next time to see some of this in 3D instead.
다음 시간에 3D로 보여드릴 테니 기대하세요